[Music]
welcome to mental health Monday it's
been a while but we are so happy to be
back with you guys thank you for joining
us this evening want to say welcome to
my co-host Dr White good to see you I
think it's been three weeks it's been
three weeks absolutely and that was not
that was not planned no it wasn't
planned that was not plan it's
interesting because um even even when
we're away though we find things to keep
our ourselves busy isn't that right oh
yes we were quite busy quite busy and
for those of you who may have watched
church service on on this past Sabbath
um and we announced that we were doing
part three on depression how many of you
watch sports or watch football there's
something that they call an audible you
know what an audible is is where the Dr
White doesn't know what I'm talking
about but he he looks at basketball not
football anyways they they they when a
coach calls an audible it's like he's
just changing like they have a play that
they were going to go with and then at
the last minute he calls an audible and
he goes with something else because he
thinks it's going to work best for that
team or play so today Dr White and I but
really mainly him first called an
audible so we're not doing depression
part three this evening but we believe
that we still have an amazing program
for you and we will be coming back to
depression and finish that up at some
point um as well because we've done two
programs and you are really here for it
it was
great um and we want to be able to
continue to give you uh that information
but we're going to be talking about the
brain and how the brain can change
itself so you don't you're not going to
want to miss this matter of fact push
share on your social media right right
at this time go ahead Dr W we we and we
love you know giving flowers where
they're where they're do uh the author
Dr Norman Norman Dees sorry if I'm
butchering the name uh he wrote a
phenomenal book on um you know
neuroplasticity and he entitled it the
brain that changes itself yes and
whenever I get a a a patient a client or
a loved one
that has experienced or know someone
who's experienced a stroke I always
refer them to the book hey pick that
book up and they'll say for the client
I'm like no for
you and that's what you said to me today
absolutely no no no not for him for you
because this will Empower you on how to
provide that person's support yes and
that's what you're going to see as we
talk about this uh this evening so this
is when you do not want to miss because
we are going to help you adjust your
mindset to really understand how best to
recover from a stroke yes and uh we're
well we'll Circle back around to that
when we start to you why we were
discussing uh that uh today but I do
want to say welcome um to brother Clint
and brother yeah and to and to Deborah
and gwendelyn very good to see you guys
on here let us know where you guys um
the others who are watching please let
us know where you are viewing from so we
can say a welcome to you um looking for
you Veronica I hope Veronica's on
because I think we made Clint and
Veronica like our probably most faithful
because they're always here so Veronica
if you're not here I'm going to be sad
because I made it a point a mental point
today to be like okay if Veronica's on
there I'm gonna make her just as special
as Clint well tell me about it and Clint
we are praying that God's gonna work
something out so we can see you at the
convocation we're just like we're
praying something miraculous is gonna
happen yeah Clint you have to come we
have to take a picture the three of us
we have to take a picture and take a
picture with your whole family to our
you know would be amazing but yes we
definitely want to to see you and
everyone else too let us hey let us know
in the chat if you guys planning on
coming uh but joyn from Arizona welcome
very I love your handle hey it's me I
love
that cool cool Melissa Hill from
Huntsville Alabama all right just down
the road from me somewhere down the road
I see Joselyn from Arizona that's a
little closer to me said Joselyn I said
joeline but yeah you're right it is
probably
Joselyn well either way but welcome yes
she is closer to you for sure um but
yeah we are happy to have all of you
here yeah today um and we just want to
welcome you again and you know from some
of you may already know um but um we had
missed three weeks because I was dealing
with a family emergency three weeks ago
uh with my brother who had a stroke and
so I had to do had to fly up to where he
lives doing an emergency um visit that
needed to happen and I was glad I was
able to go and so Dr White and I were
talking today just about that recovery
process and um and that's when he
mentioned the book and he's like why
don't we do the program on it tonight
and so that's where the audible came
from and so we believe that again you're
going to be truly blessed and we want to
jump right into it we started we started
a little bit late so we into it just to
let you guys know that you're please you
are part of this program with us you we
are co-hosts for each other but you are
also our host because you help build the
program with your questions and your
comments so if you have any questions or
comments as we are presenting please put
it in the chat and uh make this program
a great one no question and yeah let's
let's hop in um so this book is uh
really about the the miracle of
neuroplasticity and it's one thing to
say that we are fearfully and
wonderfully made but by the end of this
program you're going to have some really
concrete understanding of why we can say
that with confidence we are fearfully
and wonderfully made uh so the the book
talks about
neuroplasticity um so what exactly is
neur
plasticity so obviously with the basic
building block unit of the brain is
What's called the neuron and neurons are
designed in such a way that almost like
the way my hands are shaking each other
one neuron will basically shake the
hands of another neuron and they'll form
networks and obviously it's a lot more
complicated than what I'm Des describing
but this networking is at the basis of
our ability to engage and be aware of
existence well at one point it was
thought that that that networking was
something permanent that once formed
it's just G to stay that way
forever and the truly amazing thing
became the the the Epiphany the paradigm
shift that no actually what happens
is that can
change our brain will undergo
neuroplastic changes depending on the
environment depending on the activities
and guys depending on even your
thoughts I love it I love your analogy
so the two hands basically connecting
our you know shaking hands we'll say
that shaking hands Okay so so what I'm
hearing you say um is like so if for
some reason that
handshake stops or stop if these two
nuran stop communicating to each other
um the body can find a new way is that
is that what it is a new it'll shake
hands it can shake hands with someone
else or when you are learning something
even if it retains connection with that
neuron it may form a connection with
another neuron right um and this of
course will happen in a massive way
because the the brain has about a 100
billion neurons um so the synapses are
going into the
trillions um but yeah like I think it's
just so profound the
implication that your thoughts will
literally R Network your
mind there's so much I have to say
there's so much I because first of all I
think this is probably if preached in a
sermon format I think that
neuroplasticity is like the gospel at
its core because it's coming it's like I
can you can I can change God's saying I
can come and change you my gopel is
neuroplastic you know it's like you
don't have to stay the same but that's
not really where I was trying to go but
I just thought of that too but um I just
think like it's just when you say you
said there's one billion neurons 100
billion 100 billion billion okay 100
billions I don't know why I guess 100
billion neurons and that is such a large
number so there's such a variety of ways
that the brain has to like you're saying
heal itself oh my goodness and it's
funny that he called the brain that
changes itself because really it can
also heal itself and in a sense in a
sense um but this concept of of
neuroplasticity and even your thoughts
re networking your mind it's the reason
it used to be said if a person has a
personality disorder that can't get
better like you can't you can't say that
you can't say that because what what you
can say is we have not identified the
mechanisms that effectively rehabilitate
personality disorders you might be able
to say that but to say that there aren't
mechanisms there aren't experiences that
will help the rnetwork and transform
that person is hogwash that's it's
nonsense right nonsense so what you see
is God built us with the ability to
transform and and um with my clients we
do a lot of work uh with their thoughts
and becoming aware of their negative
thoughts and changing those thoughts and
after they put a they put a lot of work
intentional work into changing their
thoughts their their moods their
personalities you know what I'm saying
they change into a more positive
uh thinking instead of such a negative
thinking so the the first concept we
want you guys to be aware of that the
book talks about is this idea that
neuroplasticity changed old paradigms so
as as accepted as our understanding of
neuroplasticity is today at one point
the belief was that the brain wasn't
capable of that okay and so you want to
realize that these ideas evolve all
right the next thing is mental exercises
reshape the brain mental exercises
reshape the brain now you know so one of
the things that you then want to be
aware of then is man what are things I
can do that will in fact exercise my my
mind and exercise my brain
so I really struggle with hey man what's
the utility of like you know like for
example Eastern meditation you know
where it's like I just you know I just
focus on this one thought focus on this
one thought and so what what I try to do
in my brain training is I want to kind
of simulate the
activities that I'm going through the
day and I want my brain to perform the
way that I want it to so I'm never in a
situation where I'm just trying to focus
on one point focus on one point but like
for example a calcul
so I find it way more helpful to let's
say do a mental
calculation um because that simulates
the processing that I do when I'm trying
to solve a problem or if I'm trying to
analyze a situation and so me and my
daughter will do this sometimes but
we'll we'll get in we'll we'll both sit
in the room and we'll see we'll take an
an equation like 356 time 457 let's see
who can solve it first just using our
thinking you know and we'll sit quietly
in the room and we will just mentally go
through it you can do it it's just it
requires amazing Focus um but here that
sounds fun when your dad is a
psychiatrist and a medical doctor and
has fun with math those are the type of
games you
play well well this my dad was into
sports like we'd go shoot basketball or
something like that but I'm I'm kid I
think it's amazing that you do that with
well the the the payoff is though that
now as you're going through your day you
you feel like hey man I'm I'm at peace I
can I can do the processing I can do
what's necessary because it's like I got
my brain
thinking so um mental exercises can play
a really great you know role in
reshaping the brain um so that that
that's an interesting point was there
anything you wanted to say about that um
no it kind of just when I was sharing
about the different exercise I give my
clients to retrain their negative
thoughts it's it's basically on that
same line of thinking and that's what
the brain can do well absolutely and I
really hope that they take those
exercises seriously it's their
homework yeah they have to I make them
take it seriously because I remind them
every week how serious it is because the
brain is going to R Network itself like
there are going to be neuronal changes
around these thought patterns so Point
number three is the importance of
repetition so this is a great dovetail
off of what you're saying um repeated
practice is going to strengthen the
neural
connections and this is where it's
really important to understand that when
you first try to do
something a lot of times you ENC counter
failure defeat that can discourage you
from progressing and boy is that a
mistake boy is that a mistake um because
the brain is literally like making
changes not stuff you can detect per se
well except the headache you know
because you're just like man this is
this hurts right you know but it's it's
reorienting itself and so now when you
repeat it again it's
reorienting and it's reorienting and the
networks are forming yes and
unfortunately we don't we're not patient
enough to give it the structure
necessary somebody's a smart Al I know I
see that like doing that for you and
your daughter that's hilarious that's
funny har that's funny um but um but
yeah it's it's it's R networking itself
so that it's going to support the
Endeavor of your choosing yes your brain
is designed with an
elasticity to modify itself to support
the Endeavor of your choosing For Better
or For Worse so we'll talk about the
worse later on yeah I want there's a
question up there and it oh yeah sorry
what did you say Deborah what's the
difference between a massive stroke and
a mild stroke which part of the brain is
affected by both all right so let's talk
about that let's talk about what is a
stroke all right so to understand what a
stroke is um I want you to Envision a
tube which is going to be your blood
vessel
and in that in that blood vessel
obviously blood flows what exactly is
accomplished with blood flow you know
the movement of that fluid well blood
flow will do two things
simultaneously um it will bring things
to
the cells the tissues the organs it will
bring things to them so what does it
bring to them it brings the red cells
and the oxygen it brings white cells to
protect against infections and Cancers
and all that kind of stuff it brings
hormones uh that will affect how that
tissue functions um and it just brings a
host of things that cell that tissue
will need to
function simultaneously while it's
bringing things to the tissue it is also
taking things away so can you pause just
one second what's that Veronica just
said sorry I'm late and so we just want
you to know Veronica that we did a
special welcome to you because we missed
you we know noticed you weren't on but
we're glad that you're here now all
right go ahead yeah we we we shouted out
Clint um because he held it down he was
responsible no I'm kidding Veronica we
are so honored that you would be with us
look they're on vacation
in so no she kind of w up you CL you
still you and Clint are
still next yeah you're our top you're
our top that that was that was tight
Veronica I hope you guys are enjoying
your vacation by the way yes yes so yeah
back to the blood cell and the fact that
that flow is doing two things
simultaneously both bringing to the cell
the tissue the organs the organ system a
number of the chemicals the resources
that needs but it's taking things away
so it's taking away waste products it's
taking away carbon dioxide so that
movement is very very important so when
we talk about a stroke especially in a
schic stroke we are talking about
blockage in that blood vessel that's
going to stop that flow so now because
that flow has stopped that tissue the
cells the organs they are not getting
those resources the oxygen the hormones
and you know whatever else they need and
it's also not getting rid of the waste
the carbon dioxide and the other things
it needs to get out of that cell so what
do you think happens to the cells and
those tissues they start to die off they
start to die off they start to die off
all right so now your question was
what's the difference between a massive
stroke and a smaller stroke well the
bigger the blood vessel the bigger the
blood vessel the the the the uh that the
stroke is occurring in the bigger is
going to be the area that's affected all
right um and then of course the smaller
the blood vessel sometimes the smaller
the area that is affected but it gets
really complicated because in the body
there are small areas that might be
doing really important things um so even
though it might be a small area it could
still be devast ating
consequences so that's why it's hard to
talk about small versus big the other
thing is again this is fearfully and
wonderfully made um part of the reason
that sometimes strokes and blockages
don't cause the massive deficits that
you would expect is because for example
the blood supply of the brain is a
circle it's circular so it really takes
advantage of collateral
circulations right meaning if the blood
doesn't get there one way well then
maybe it'll get there another way and
you know and so and and that's the other
thing about when you exercise when you
exercise there are hormones that are
released that stimulate new blood vessel
ination of the tissue and so this is why
this can be really good stuff so anyway
um the bottom line is that's why it can
be a little complicated to say well is
it a big stroke is it a small stroke and
then the other thing you want to know
about Strokes is while there can be es
schic there can be blockage that will
disrupt the blood getting to where it
needs to get to and and leaving there
can also be hemorrhagic Strokes
hemorrhagic means rather than blockage
now the tissue
ruptured okay so you'll hear that hey
the person had an aneurysm so an
aneurysm is like when that blood vessel
starts to balloon as the Integrity of
the wall starts to weaken or become
defective then it can weaken and weaken
until the aneurysm ruptures okay uh and
so that's where you can get but the
bottom line the the the central thing
that's occurring is there is a
disruption in the
flow of to that tissue um so I hope that
answered your question about you know
large versus smaller
Strokes yes those were that was a great
uh answer and resp response we were on
number three and you were talking about
the importance of repetition and I just
wanted to to share this point too like I
was saying um when I with my clients we
do um you know do work on um well
something else that we do is as I have
them do is positive affirmations so
they're repeating every day the same
thing so I I I usually tell them to do
three sets in the morning in the
afternoon in the evening and I have them
I tell them to look in the mirror look
in your cell phone if you don't have a
mirror like I want them to hear
themselves and see themselves say the
words of you know I am I am good enough
I'm just giving examples I am good
enough I am smart I am uh worthy of Love
whatever the affirmation needs to be and
they're saying this three times a day
all you know every single day and after
some time that neuroplasticity their
minds those neurons it's they're
changing they're changing from this
negative connection and belief negative
thoughts about themselves to positive
ones so that takes time though ites time
it takes time to even believe it right
but it's so key to do it I think that's
wonderful that you do that to your
clients um because you it's like
bloodless neurosurgery yes that good
therapists love that good practitioners
are doing bloodless
neurosurgery like we are literally
helping to reshape the the brain and of
course when you when you leverage
activities like what you just described
you are you are literally impacting
their brain for the better so a lot of
times people want to minimize things
like therapy you know mental health
coaching but like what you're doing is
you are helping this person think
differently you know you're helping them
you're you're you're you're helping them
rewire their brain right um and um and
so so think about think about how a
brain is wired towards those positive
thoughts but then think also about how a
brain is wired towards negative thoughts
right if you've ever experienced a
person who's super negative just imagine
man what how is your brain wired clearly
I see how it's wired right well you're
gonna have to have patience to get it
unwired that's not GNA just happen in a
day you know that's why when you talk to
a person be like cheer
up right just and I and I even tell my
clients I was like you know when you
start these positive affirmations
because you're wired for the negative
you're going to feel like you're lying
to yourself it's going to feel awkward
but I want you to keep saying it anyways
and eventually it stop it stops to be so
awkward and you start to not think
you're lying to yourself anymore and you
actually start to believe it but it's a
process it's a long process this is
interesting um uh so we had uh we have a
math here we have a math professor here
so he might I think he wants to
challenge you at some point oh my
goodness what did I start I don't know C
Professor scare me I'm just saying I'm
just negative thought I need to change
that okay exactly uh tante they scared
you until now until now until now that's
right um Candy um you asked why did
people why what or why do people have a
heart attack after a stroke I love this
this is a fantastic question are one of
the things that'll happen is uh if you
hear a person had a stroke let's say in
their brain um sometimes the thinking is
okay well they have a problem just in
that particular vasculature they're
that's so that affects the blood vessels
of the brain and what we don't realize
is that look you know a
problem somewhere is very likely an
indicator that there might be a problem
everywhere right and I'm saying that
Loosely um but
just if you're if you've got a lot of
atherosclerotic plaque buildup there's a
good chance it's not just occurring in
one area so for
example you may have heard this before
but erectile dysfunction is sometimes
described as the canary in the
landmine it's not the land is it the
landmine um Canary and the mine Canary
and the mine
yeah um meaning back in the day of
course for those of you who may not be
aware I guess when the canary died it
was a sign that you you guys are exposed
to gas I think right but the bottom line
being it's blood vessels it's it's
patent functional blood vessels that
allow for an erection and when that goes
away it's a sign that those blood
vessels might be damaged well in like
manner it's probably not just blood
vessels there that's affected it could
be all over the body so uh a an es schic
stroke you know or a stroke in one part
of the body it could also mean that
there might be a stroke that the blood
vessels that supply the heart might be
problematic um so that's just one
possibility um but the bottom line is
the answer to your question is there it
can be a myriad of reasons as to why a
person may have a heart attack um Myriad
of reasons why a person may have a
stroke um so that but I just want you to
be aware that this is why it's it's it
can be so awesome to try to live in ways
where you reduce pla deposition where
you reduce damage to your blood vessels
because it's very likely that it's going
to be damaged all over the body all
right really really quick before we go
into that question I think it's a
perfect time uh for you to um speak
about uh The Mastermind Institute right
I well thank you so much for that sis
well so uh after you know 133 years of
formal training and 20 years
practicing uh what I saw was was pretty
clearly and and designing treatment team
plans I saw what worked I saw what
didn't work and one of the things that
led me to develop was uh my seven vitals
process and uh now I'm doing more and
more coaching Through The Mastermind
Institute so that if you are interested
in exploring coaching uh with me I I
texted you a link but you probably don't
have that link ready right you know what
I I I don't so just email me at info@
The Mastermind Institute just email me
at info@ The Mastermind Institute um if
you are interested in exploring what
what possibilities there are to um coach
with me so it's info The Mastermind
Institute and you could probably put it
in the chat if I'm dialoging with them
time to put it in the chat and if our
Queen producer Amar was here she would
have had it ready to go just W to uh ask
you guys to keep Amar in prayer because
she's she's healing she wasn't uh
feeling well uh recently and so that's
why she's not here to this evening but
hopefully she'll be back next week uh so
we're looking forward to that um we do
have there it goes you were
quick so yes please check that out
that's in the that's in the chat you can
click that link and you'll get all that
information that Dr White was talking
about um absolutely yes so that question
how does the brain overcome deep seated
guilt and the easy answer is that that
process we were already talking about is
the beginning way but go ahead well well
um the implication of those words deep
seated you know they they kind of clue
you in on what's going on um it's
deep-seated meaning it's deeply
networked you know so that the
networking is going to be pretty
extensive in terms of just the way that
that person is thinking their rumination
well what do you think that's doing to
their neural networking it's really
building around that process well the
same way it was built it was built
through what repetition they repeated
the idea over and over and over and over
again so guess where healing is going to
come from
repetition you know um but I gotta tell
you Ari like this to me is why our
approach is just so fascinating in terms
of mental health um there are important
questions that you would go over with
that person
um and you're really trying to get at
you know why are you so guilty why are
you prone um to guilt and so often it's
interesting listening to what happened
in your early life um because as people
go on in their path in their Journey
what you see is there are often defining
events there are there are defining
events um and those events will shape
such important parts of you especially
how it unfolded did you get therapy did
you not get therapy did you get
counseling did you not get and it will
affect who you are and how you are and
and so it's it's really really important
to understand what's the person's
biology so how were they wired in the
first place then what are the things
that happened that led them and then you
can start to then formulate okay what's
the experience I can design that's going
to rehabilitate the person and at the
core rehabilitate the way they
think it formed through repetition okay
so they had a biological predisposition
then they had life experiences that just
revved the engine up and it it it
supported the wiring and then they get
to this point where okay well now let's
understand the wiring and let's put in
place an experience that will rewire
that brain right but the good news is
change is possible yes change is
possible our brains are not like these
metal structures where tomorrow provided
there's no heat when I come it's going
to look exactly like this provid fall or
whatever not your brain not your brain
your brain depending on your experiences
can absolutely
transform so it's just you got to do the
Reps you got to do the Reps what were
you gonna say sis I was gonna say you
got to do the Reps because it like your
brain wasn't wired with this negative
thinking or emotions or feelings
overnight that's years of the different
experiences in your life that has caused
you to be wired that way and so I like
to explain to my clients like it's just
it's tightly wired together and so when
you're doing the repetition you're just
slowly every day
unwiring that thinking process and it's
a beautiful thing that it could happen
right that it's even possible I still I
like to tell people that
neuroplasticity my this is how I feel
this is my opinion is besides Jesus
dying on the cross our biggest gift to
us as humans because as sinful humans
without neuroplasticity there would be
absolutely no hope for us to mean like
so but the the capacity for
transformation like the cap it's just so
amazing if you will just be patient with
the process if you just don't demand
that the first time you do it it's
perfect yeah if you will allow for the
Reps yeah you know I I I have to record
content from from time to time at tante
you should see the first try oh my
goodness like what's wrong with me right
yeah why did I mess up that word that do
it again do it again and you do it again
and you do it again and you do it again
it's like oh now that's what I thought
it would sound like by time yeah and
like working out at the gym is the same
principles like you just have to be
consistent and then after a month you
start to see stuff and then after two
months and three months and people think
Pastor Meers just poof turned into like
to be a very muscular man looking that's
not all natural no it's not all natural
you give away his secret you guys
wouldn't believe how small he was when I
met him all I can say is genetically
they are just very thin framed um
genetically and well he decided he
wanted something different and he works
at it all the time well it's it's a
testimony to his tenacity so Props props
to the brother yes yeah um well uh I
love Clint statement here what what were
you gonna say no no no I say we're on
number four but but let's Clint no I
know I saw the Hallelujah There's Hope
for all yes R plant the second amen
there is hope for all that's the gospel
no question and uh Clint said it's
interesting how words reveal our is
infrastructure our world yo and Clint
can we take it one step further like if
you want to see how you're thinking look
at your
environment look at your environment
your environment is the outgrowth of
your
thinking there needs to be like an
atomic bomb when I say that your your
environment right now as you look around
if you're a Amazed by it then you've
been having some amazing thinking
patterns and if you are frustrated by it
you've been having some frustrated
thinking patterns but here is the
awesome part the awesome part is if you
want it to get amazing start shifting
your thinking start shifting your
thinking and and it's totally possible
totally POS so I I love that Clinton and
this why that's why my slogan is Master
your mind so you can can master your
life master your mind so you can there's
some great comments in the chat uh candy
says the enemy wants us to believe we
aren't forgiven like we can't change
type of thing and then Felicia says wow
the power of
repetition absolutely and yeah they're
really they're really getting excited
about the change that can be had well
now this is now number four takes us to
the whole point that we did this why we
did this
did we go ahead of the author on the
book on the outline and we might have
went a little ahead of him well I mean
sort of but um but for number four the
the point that they went to is recovery
from brain damage recovery from brain
damage so now imagine if you think that
the brain is fixed then when it gets
damaged your thinking would be that that
damage is fixed right and that brain
that the the book the brain that changes
itself shatters that it just shatters
that idea absolutely shatters it um and
what it talks about is recovery from
brain damage so it gives this phenomenal
story of a
scientist whose brother I guess was a
psychiatrist and their father was a
professor at one of the schools I don't
know if it was you know um in New York
or what have you but whatever the case
the the the father suffered a massive
stroke the brother who's a psychiatrist
actually um went home and he said you
know what we crawl before we can walk so
let me get him crawling and so he has
this man crawling everywhere and
crawling and crawling and crawling and
so of course the neighbors are getting
upset they're like he's making fun this
is this is outrageous but whatever the
case he keeps at it keeps at it and
don't you know before long his father
crawled effectively can walk effectively
and his father was tenacious as well so
before you know it he like is doing one
finger at the typewriter and he
progresses and progresses until he
regains full function to where he can go
back be a professor the father ends up
dying on a backpacking trip in the
mountains that's how functional he got
and then when they actually studied his
brain they see that there was a massive
area that had involved the stroke but
the
recovery involved the brain reassigning
function reassigning function and so
it's just such of an amazing story yes
it is uh regarding the recovery from
brain damage but that's like one story
then they talked about a um an Institute
called the pots
Institute and this was an Institute that
was famous for its aggressive rehabil
itation it was incredibly aggressive so
they would get outstanding outcomes like
people who had you know had strokes and
they'd been paralyzed for a long time
their rehab was so aggressive they they
would rehabilitate or restore function
to a person that had been stroked out
for like you know 10 years 12 years and
so they thought oh I'm not going to get
this back but they were so persistent so
rigorous that they were effective in
restoring function now ly you know
consult your healthare provider please
do not get crazy because because really
at the heart of good rehab it's staying
right on The Cutting Edge of that person
you got to stay right on The Cutting
Edge you cannot overwhelm a person right
you know or else they'll just give up
it's when you stay right on The Cutting
Edge and you're able to encourage them
through those dark moments so this is
not to encourage you to go crazy but
this is to encourage you to understand
were built to recover yes you are not
doomed you are not doomed by necessarily
you know a stroke the potential for
Recovery is amazing we are fearfully and
wonderfully made fearfully and
wonderfully made so glory to God yeah
that's the section on recovery from
brain damage which I just think
absolutely amazing so the stories in the
book that are littered throughout the
book Dr dege you just did an amazing job
picked that book up um get the audio
book because I don't know it's just hard
for me to read books nowadays but the
Audio I can listen while I'm driving of
course in Southern California you can
listen to like one book a day because of
the traffic much for that traffic that's
what that's what I'm saying I was like I
yeah don't know how far you have to go
to work but even if it's only five
minutes away this would take you
probably an hour right it's amazing as
you're skipping around town you know
it's like you get through like good four
or five chapters and yes knocked out a
book or when you're exercising in the
gym that's right or when you're
exercising in the gym sensory
substitution the brain can adapt number
five the brain can adapt sensory input
from one sense to compensate for the
loss of another such as using touch or
sound to interpret visual information
now what that's getting at is that for
example the back of the brain is
normally thought of as the visual cortex
for example so now here it is now if you
got damage to the back and now the
person had some problem in vision and
with time maybe they
restore um Vision what exactly took
place there and so what that's getting
at as far as sensory substitution is
there like throughout the brain you can
get reassigning of function there is
tissue that can actually carry out
functions that might have at one point
been assigned to one part of the brain
and now it's assigned to another part of
the brain um so again Concepts that
confine the brain you find that the
brain is like don't don't don't confine
me I I I operate above your
limitations the name of the book again
Felicia is um the brain that CH the
brain that changes itself the brain that
changes Itself by Dr Norman Dodges
goodbye Felicia I've always wanted to
say that
please don't go anywhere
Felicia I've always want to say that I'm
just Felicia so you got to you help to
fulfill a dream Felicia she she probably
gets that a lot I'm sure all right
cortical periods oh yeah all right so
now number six critical periods versus
lifelong change so while some functions
like language Acquisitions are easier
During certain developmental Windows
neuroplasticity proves that significant
changes are possible at any age okay
okay and so it you know it used to be
believed this is why the there yes you
know children will tend to learn at a
more rapid pace and you know their
Investments are very very you know
highend if they're learning languages
that can be easier they're learning
musical instruments and a lot of
processes in fact you're here with a lot
of Champions I started at 4 and I
started you know so there is definitely
an advantage but please do not be
discouraged Ed um to take up new
activities let me see Felicia said I
have a grandson who has autism can this
work for him oh what a question Felicia
that's a great question I have a
grandson who has autism can this work
for him I once had a friend who um his
daughter was autistic and so he asked me
hey man what what should be my Approach
and training her and um Felicia the the
the key is to stay on The Cutting Edge
but stimulation stimulation stimulation
and when I say that first of all work
with your healthcare provider but what I
mean is you want to stay on their
Cutting Edge and support you know their
activities so it's like hey let I want
to teach you this and so you see what it
is that they can learn and then you
adapt to it and you keep you know you
keep doing the gentle stimulation now
autism is you know because sometimes
like they really don't want to be
stimulated in certain ways or it might
be light it might be colors it might be
different things
so what's true in autism is so true with
any other child have to take the time to
understand your child right like you and
how they learn and how they learn so
there's the proverb train up a child in
the way he should go and when he's old
he will not depart from it Child
Development number one and what 101 and
what it's basically saying is train when
you train something if you're G to
effectively train anything you have to
understand that thing you got to know
where it is and where you want it to get
to and have the patience and not demand
that it get to where you want to go at
your pace you have to be patient and be
creative and say okay well this didn't
work well maybe we can try it this way
well maybe we can try it this way but
the idea is understand where that child
is and then come up with the
interventions to help them to
develop um so that that to me and what
on Earth do you think is happening while
you're doing that change that that
training their their brain is changing
their brain is networking so as much as
possible you are offering interaction
where where possible where it respects
how they want to interact um you are
teaching them hey this is appropriate
this is not appropriate but it it it
really follows the same framework right
that that it would with a child that
didn't have autism it's just you might
need more patient in certain ways right
and by the way look for their skills
yeah oh they have them their skills
because those all humans are blessed
with an aptitude so they they may very
well be gifted in a certain area so
watch out for that um and and and and
don't presume don't pre-label before
you've actually been given them an
opportunity so it really follows the
same format um
patience understanding and Innovative
intervening like and lot of patience and
and then I think it was Felicia Felicia
and some self care for you too right
because that patience is not simple and
I'm gonna say this is for Ashley too
because she has three children which I
have three children with autism 11 and
12 self-care self-care selfcare don't
forget that don't forget that part um
but yeah lot a tremendous amount of okay
how do I approach this child and how do
I approach this child and and what does
this child love and how do I leverage
that understanding to incentivize them
oh you love this okay well this is how
we're going to reward you um so so lot
of patience a lot of people and for
Ashley like exactly what you said Dr
white but for Ashley you have three uh
children with autism they're three
different children with autism so they
may learn three different ways and
that's perfectly fine and the good thing
is that neuroplasticity is available to
everyone and then but just like with um
or it's possible I should say with
everyone but then with the autistic
child it will just look a little
different on how they learn that but
everyone has the same hope it just may
look a little different but the best way
to frustrate yourself is to go in with
this predetermined idea of this is how
it's is and it it of course can Clash
with the reality of what you encounter
and then everyone's frustrated rather
than hey I really need to take the time
to understand how does this child like
to learn how does how do they learn
boundary setting how do I incentivize
them and it's going to be different for
each one very likely um so but hats off
to you oh and by the way a lot of prayer
a lot of prayer fasting and and and all
that kind of good stuff um never mind
the biological stuff what are what are
the nutrients that help their brains
what are uh when are when is it that you
should be feeding them and how do you
keep them on a schedule so that they
sleep um so very important it's all a
system have you heard of using sound
frequencies with autism that is out of
my depth I was just gonna say it was out
of M too I maybe Dr White I do not I
don't know anything about that Ashley um
my my just want to be as clear as
possible yes all right let me see
critical next number seven is the Dark
Side of
neuroplasticity and so basically you'll
recall I said the brain is designed to
help you in the Endeavor of your
choosing for good or for bad and so what
you'll see what you'll see for example
with a person who is addicted let's say
they're addicted to porn let's say even
the sound of keys will be a trigger even
the sound of keys will will be a trigger
and like a person for example who's
addicted to heroin or alcohol
did you know that when they have
resolved to
relapse if if they were experiencing
withdrawal the withdrawal actually
improves a little like this is how
profound the mind is okay so I'm we're
talking about it's just so profound but
how when you go around a certain
neighborhood if if if you're an addict
just certain places trigger you just a
given memory can trigger you because
your brain is wired around the use of
that substance um so sometimes you know
I'll be you know saying to some of my my
patients struggling with addiction um so
uh you're G to go to a meeting oh that
meeting is way too far I'd be like uh
just act like your connect was over
there right would you find a way if
you're connect was over there oh you
know that
doc I'm saying I'm saying the same
creativity you use and the substance use
use that in your recovery and one of the
amazing things you see is people who
recover from addictions become amazing
salespeople they will lead movements
because they have figured out now how to
switch and how
to harness the power of that addictive
behavior into recovery behavior and
amazing things happen um so that that's
the Dark Side of neuroplasticity you can
become habituated to things that do not
serve you and we can go from addiction
um to chemicals to substances to
processes and behaviors addicted to
gossip addicted to lying you know
addicted to bullying people um so the
the brain can just become habituated man
why would you want that why would you
want that so that's the Dark Side of
neuroplasticity
yes you know we are at that time it it's
it's a lot of and I know we have a few
more points and we could go even deeper
in the study I'm thinking guys I think
we might we're calling another audible
that we might do a part two next week
might do part two it's only two the role
of attention application and therapy and
Rehab which we did a lot of we did we
talked a lot about so we can we can go
back to the the the um last part of
depression for for next week okay
because we hammered home the power of
therapy um and Rehab yes and so just
really quickly the role of attention
focused attention is critical for
rewiring the brain as it engages the
processes needed for Learning and
adapting so this is where I talked about
my daughter and I doing this like mental
calculating you know and practicing
focus and
attention um so so yeah I go grab the
book um
phenomenal book you know some if you've
had a stroke or if you know somebody
who's had a stroke Empower yourself to
understand how best to help them uh so
by the time you end up reading that book
and you see some some person struggling
and they're approaching a door you know
normally you'd run up and be like n let
me get the door for you no let them
struggle let them get it because that
struggle communicates to the brain we
need you and we need those neurons to
inovate those muscles and they're going
to get better obviously Guys Don't Be
Cruel right but don't be but but
yourself do that please don't do that um
but I want you to understand the role it
plays um of use it or lose it the brain
is definitely built on the system of use
it or lose it so please use it for sure
over to well I just want to say thank
you to everyone for joining us this
evening and are plant the second yes be
here next week you plan to come bring
some friends with you because all of you
add to our programming um and so we're
just so thankful to have each and every
one of you so again share this on your
social media because everybody needs to
hear this information that
neuroplasticity is is what is our brains
can change and so that is the most
hopeful thing for every human being on
on this planet so share with your
friends your family um and just be
blessed and we're just thankful that you
were here and we look forward to seeing
you next week see you next week everyone
bye bye bye bye